<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To all that want peace with God to the sheep everywhere not brought home, ... plainly published, concerning the way of life, and of the gradual comings forth of death through law ... / ... Humphry Smith.</title>
            <author>Smith, Humphrey, d. 1663.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60448</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4079</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6668</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11966640</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11966640</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51734</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60448)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51734)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 824:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To all that want peace with God to the sheep everywhere not brought home, ... plainly published, concerning the way of life, and of the gradual comings forth of death through law ... / ... Humphry Smith.</title>
                  <author>Smith, Humphrey, d. 1663.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 19 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Wilson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51734:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>To all that want Peace with God; To the SHEEP Everywhere not brought home; to the thirſty breathing Soul, and to the Seed, though in Captivity, among, and in the midſt of all PROFESSORS; <hi>Greetings of Love, Mercy, and Peace, from God the Father of the Living.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By way of EXPOSTULATION, In the <hi>Demonſtration</hi> of his Spirit, plainly publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Concerning the way of life,</hi> and of the <hi>gradual com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings forth of Death through the Law,</hi> and the vail, unto the <hi>living Subſtance,</hi> received of <hi>them,</hi> who follows the <hi>Spirit,</hi> in its ſeveral <hi>manifeſtations,</hi> through the <hi>diſpenſations</hi> unto him that <hi>diſtributeth</hi> a porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>the Word of Faith</hi> unto every Man.</p>
            <p>From a Servant of the Lord, <hi>Humphry Smith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Wilſon,</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread Eagle</hi> and <hi>Windmill,</hi> in <hi>Martins</hi> near <hi>Alderſgate,</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:51734:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:51734:2"/>
            <head>To all that want peace with God; to the Sheep every where not brought home; to the thirſty breathing Soul, and to the Seed, though in Captivity, among, and in the midſt of all Profeſſors; <hi>Greetings of Love, Mercy, and Peace from God the Father of the Living.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>VVHere the bowels are not ſhut up, nor the heart darkned, and where that doth not bear rule, which ſtoppeth the ear, and cloſeth the eye; and where prejudice and rebellion againſt the <hi>Light,</hi> with the wiſdom of the fleſh, through that knowledge which puffeth up, hath not wholly eaten up, devoured, got over, and wholly overcome that tender principle, which once moved in the heart, towards that <hi>being</hi> of the living ſubſtance. There may my words take entrance, and unto ſuch, who feels that which breaths to God, and who are willing to be ſatisfied con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the living truth of his Son, and who would receive the truth if they knew it, and do yet more deſire after the power of God, than all the temporal things that are ſeen, and who are yet come no further, than the reading of the Law, the Prieſts, the Tyths, nor that Religion that makes nothing perfect, and who are come no further than the outward <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> or <hi>ſhadow,</hi> or <hi>Figure,</hi> or ſuch things, which are to be left behind, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. or who are come no further than the Supper, or the Death, and ſo not yet ſaved by his life, nor drunk of that which ſaveth, and is to cleanſe from all that, which ſeperateth from God; after whom, and the incomes of his love immortal, whoſoever truly deſireth, and is willing to receive the power of his life, and come in Covenant with the Lord;</p>
            <p>Such may lend me an ear a little, and you are them who may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive ſome benefit hereby; for behold I write in plainneſs of the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51734:3"/> things of God, my heart being enlarged with abundance of his peace, in which there is good will towards men, that you might come to draw near to the <hi>Witneſs;</hi> the Teſtimony whereof, is <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the vail,</hi> which vail is over the heart, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 15. and is not done away, but as you come to be in him, who is given for a witneſs, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55. 4. by believing in the Light, <hi>John</hi> 12. 36. and ſo to have the witneſs in you, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5. 10. and you to be in it; and that you may come to participate of Gods in dwellings, and feel the oyl which will laſt for ever; therefore I proceed thus:</p>
            <p>How can I but look back a little with an eye of pitty over thoſe, who yet are, where once I was, when the darkneſs was over the earth, &amp; the cloud of error compaſſed me as well as others, ſurely I cannot now be ſo unmindful of them that are yet <hi>loſt,</hi> as not to have compaſſion upon the Out-caſt of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> or to conceal from them theſe things of ſo great concernment, but rather as the Lord of my life hath opened to me, will I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>each forth my hand towards the weak, &amp; utter my voyce to the priſoner of hope, and ſhew unto the meek in the earth, how the inviſible God hath led his ſeed, and is leading his remnant through, and out of the varieties of things, unto the one thing it ſelf, from whence the various things, gifts, and m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>niſtrations doth come.</p>
            <p>Now, that which is chiefly in my heart, to write for the ſeeds ſake, is, Firſt, <hi>Something concerning the Miniſtration of</hi> Moſes, (when he was upon earth.) Secondly, <hi>Concerning the Miniſtration of Chriſt,</hi> (whil'ſt he was upon earth.) Thirdly, and chiefly, <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Miniſtration of the Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>Firſt, Concerning <hi>Moſes</hi> Miniſtration, <hi>(when he was upon earth)</hi> which was to laſt till <hi>Shiloe</hi> came, or until the time of Reformation.</head>
               <p>AS concerning <hi>Moſes Miniſtration,</hi> to wit, the <hi>Law, Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi> or <hi>Death,</hi> with the Prieſts Offering, and worldly Sanctuary, and an outward Tabernacle, and dayly Offerings for ſin, and Store-houſes for the Levites, Strangers, Fatherleſs, and Widdows, having the Ark of the Teſtimony within the vail, and the mercy ſeat covered, and the golden pot, and the people to ſeek the Law at the Prieſts mouth, whereby their knowledge is preſerved,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:51734:3"/> and many profit much thereby, and come day by day, and year by year unto that which they eſteem a place of holy worſhip, and Ordinances of God. And notwithſtanding the Prieſts of <hi>Moſes</hi> Law, were made by the Law of God, yet that Prieſt-hood chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and the Law changeth, and the very glory of all this paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth away; for this d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d once ſeem glorious unto me, and many more which o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> diſcovered ſin, though it made nothing per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and with much delight was the reading of the Law and the Prophets hearkned unto, and the daily confeſſion of ſin, (but the vail is over the heart whilſt <hi>Moſes</hi> is Preacht) and ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces morning and evening with the long prayers, which the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers thereunto, were not at all: hereby made perfect, as pertaining to the conſcience, though it had a ſhaddow of good things to come, yet the glory therof comes to be done away. Then how much more will the very glory of the moſt glorious appearance of that Miniſtry periſh, &amp; be done away, which cometh ſhort of this, and hath not ſo much as the image of this, which was as a ſhaddow. O weak and beggarly things, that are found among thoſe Prieſts now, and their followers, who come ſhort of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> Miniſtry, for he directed them to Chriſt the ſubſtance, and ſo his Miniſtration comes to be done away, as Chriſt comes to be received; for <hi>Moſes</hi> did not ſeek to uphold his Prieſts, or Law, or tythes, or any thing elſe, when Chriſt ſhould come, who is the end of the Law, but did write of him, and notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding his Miniſtry and Prieſts, he ſaid, he that would not hearken unto him, ſhould be cut off, and ſaid, <hi>the Lord will raiſe up</hi> (mark the words) <hi>raiſe up,</hi> the Lord ſhall <hi>raiſe up a Prophet,</hi> and when the Prophet was come, he ſaid, <hi>I am the Light, and I am me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>k and low in heart,</hi> and this is to be raiſed up which is meek, <hi>for to them that ſate in darkneſs Light hath ſprung up:</hi> and the ſoul that hearkneth not to the Prophet, <hi>which ſprings up</hi> ſhal be cut off, for truth <hi>ſpringeth up</hi> out of the earth, <hi>and Chriſt is the Truth,</hi> and he ſaid, <hi>I am the Light,</hi> which is the horn of ſalvation that God <hi>raiſeth up,</hi> to be <hi>a Light</hi> to lighten the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and is the ſalvation of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and ſo the ſoul is to hearken to that which God <hi>raiſeth up,</hi> and that is it which condemneth ſin (under it) who is like unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> whoſe Miniſtry <hi>diſcovers ſin,</hi> and ſo <hi>Moſes</hi> directed unto Chriſt, (who puts away the ſin) and <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid of the glory of <hi>Moſes</hi> Miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51734:4"/> that it was no glory, in reſpect of the glory of the Miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Spirit, and the glorious Miniſtry of the Spirit was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, after he who had a body prepared, had ſuffered the cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of his body, and the Prophets ſearched diligently to ſee the glory that was to be after the ſufferings of Chriſt, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 10. 11.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But the thing intended,</hi> That <hi>Moſes</hi> when he was upon earth, directed unto <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and gave commandment <hi>that they ſhould hearken unto him,</hi> (who ſaid, <hi>I am the Light) &amp; this is one Tittle of the Law, that the light be hearkned unto,</hi> who is the end of the <hi>Law,</hi> and the <hi>ſuſtance,</hi> and he that offendeth herein, is guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of all; and this is that in which all the large Miniſtrations of <hi>Moſes</hi> is included, that <hi>Chriſt the Light</hi> the <hi>true Prophet</hi> be <hi>hearkned unto</hi> and <hi>obeyed,</hi> that by <hi>hearing</hi> and <hi>obeying</hi> his voyce, (or the word in the heart) they might come from under the <hi>Law</hi> and the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and that <hi>which waxeth old,</hi> unto <hi>the life</hi> and <hi>obedience</hi> of him, who abides a <hi>Prieſt</hi> for ever, even the <hi>Lord of that glory,</hi> which laſteth for evermore.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Concerning Chriſt and his Miniſtration, <hi>(when he was upon earth)</hi> and his work which he finiſhed.</head>
               <p>ANd when he cometh, which <hi>Moſes</hi> commandeth <hi>to hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken unto,</hi> even <hi>Chriſt</hi> the <hi>true Prophet, the Light of the World, the living Miniſter, the end of the Law,</hi> who had a body prepared to do the will of the <hi>Father,</hi> which was in him <hi>the man Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> he ſaith, <hi>follow me,</hi> and he took up his Croſs and paſſed through the <hi>death</hi> &amp; the <hi>vail;</hi> &amp; ſo being made perfect through ſufferings, attained that glory, which he had with the Father before he had a body, which body, was prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to do the <hi>Fathers will,</hi> whoſe will was, that all men ſhould be ſaved; therefore <hi>Chriſt</hi> taſted death for every man, and roſe again for the Juſtification of thoſe that believe in him, who ſaid, <hi>I am the Light,</hi> and is ſate down at the right hand of God, who is a Spirit eternally in the Heavens, aſcended up out of the ſight of them, which gaſeth after that body, which is gone out of their ſight, even he, <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> hid from <hi>ages</hi> and <hi>genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:51734:4"/> now made manifeſt <hi>to deſtroy the works of the Devil,</hi> being meek and low in the heart, he ſaith <hi>learn of me:</hi> Then not of the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> nor any longer of <hi>Moſes,</hi> for the Law is the <hi>School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter to Chriſt,</hi> who being come, calleth one from the Cuſtome, another from going to bury the dead, another from queſtoning and reaſoning what this man, or another ſhould do, that he might not ſtand looking out at others, but himſelf to follow the Light, ſaying, <hi>follow thou me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thoſe that followed him when he was upon earth, ſaw his <hi>miracles,</hi> and heard <hi>his parables,</hi> and eat of <hi>the outward bread</hi> and were <hi>filled,</hi> (though many now eat and are not filled) and they had his body among them, and they came to the <hi>Baptiſme</hi> and the <hi>Supper, but Chriſt himſelf Baptiſed not;</hi> and when he was upon earth he ſaid, <hi>I go to the Father,</hi> and <hi>I go to prepare a place for you,</hi> and he ſaid, <hi>whether I go ye know;</hi> and he ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>follow me, and except a man deny himſelf aud take up his Croſs and follow me, he cannot be my Diſciple;</hi> and he ſaid, <hi>my ſheep hear my voyce, and they followed me, and he entred within the vail,</hi> (and the vail is over the heart) <hi>and was made perfect through ſufferings,</hi> and is ſate down in the <hi>Majeſty</hi> on <hi>high, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified with God the Father, and the Father was in him,</hi> even the fullneſs of God, <hi>and that which may be known of God is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt in thee;</hi> and he ſaid, <hi>he had finiſhed the work that the Father gave him to do,</hi> and ſo the Fathers will was accompliſhed and done, for which the body was prepared; he ſaid, <hi>now glorifie me Father, with the ſame glory which I had with thee from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning;</hi> and he that ſpake in the body abideth for ever, who ſad, <hi>a body haſt thou prepared me,</hi> which body being crucified, he took up <hi>his life again,</hi> and then thoſe that did know him thiree dayes before, knew him not, and he aſcended, and a cloud received him out of the ſight of certain men, who never found him unto this day, for he remaineth out of the ſight of moſt that profeſs him, and as the lightening in the <hi>Clouds of Heaven</hi> doth he come again, and every eye ſhall ſee <hi>him, that condemneth ſin;</hi> and the Kingdome of Heaven <hi>is within you,</hi> and yet the <hi>blind</hi> cannot <hi>ſee,</hi> nor the <hi>deaf hear.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this was he that <hi>Moſes</hi> commanded to <hi>hear,</hi> who ſaid, he that is with you ſhall be in you, &amp; he that was <hi>with</hi> or <hi>without,</hi> was to go away; and that which was to be received <hi>within,</hi> he
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51734:5"/> ſaid ſhould abide with them for ever, and the Spirit of truth, was to lead into all truth, for though the body was prepared to do Gods will, yet they by it were not led into all truth, but ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times underſtood it not, though he ſpake <hi>Spirit,</hi> and <hi>Life;</hi> and moreover they went away and ſome fled from the truth, and <hi>Peter</hi> denyed him that was the truth; and ſo ſuch as have got a profeſſion of the truth <hi>without them,</hi> and not the Spirit <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in</hi> to lead into all truth, ſuch fly in the day of tryal, from that truth they profeſs, and ſome deny it rather than ſuffer with, or for it, and herein, them called <hi>Baptiſts</hi> alſo, have not come ſhort; and ſome of them have bowed to the Beaſt, and ſo it is with many who profeſs Chriſt, and truth <hi>without them,</hi> even as with thoſe who underſtood not the <hi>Parables;</hi> nor could not caſt out the unclean Spirits, ſo that Chriſt was and is grieved, when he hath been ſo long <hi>with,</hi> and profeſſed, and followed <hi>without,</hi> and yet not come to that faith which purifieth the heart, whereby to caſt out the unclean <hi>within,</hi> as thou maiſt read in thy ſelf.</p>
               <p>And therefore Chriſt, when he was upon earth, did often ſpeak unto them, of what was yet to come, and I do ſeldome read or take notice, that he did ſo often Preach, and repeat any one thing unto them, as that of the Spirit to come, ſaying that <hi>it</hi> (mark the Spirit) <hi>would lead into all truth,</hi> and ſeeing their weakneſs, and unbelief, <hi>Mar.</hi> 16. 14. he by the often repetition thereof, did as it were the more chiefly to ingage their hearts to wait for, &amp; ſeek after the incomes of that which ſhould comfort them, and abide with them, when his body was gone from them, whether they could not come; and to this one thing doth he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect them in various expreſſions, as of his going to the Father, &amp; coming again, and ſaith he, <hi>I will pray the Father, &amp; he ſhall give you another Comforter, even the Spirit of truth, whom the World cannot receive,</hi> John 12. 16. <hi>and many things Jeſus did, which if it ſhould be all written, the world might not contain the books,</hi> John 21. 25. <hi>and many things he ſpake unto them,</hi> Acts 2. 40. and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et there was ſomething to come to be waited for, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be received, which was more <hi>than all this,</hi> for ſaid he, <hi>theſe things have I ſpoken unto you, being yet preſent with you;</hi> but <hi>the comforter, mark</hi> the word, <hi>but</hi> intimateth ſomething grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or more than what was ſpoken to them, whilſt he was with
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:51734:5"/> them, for he ſaith, <hi>he that is with you ſhall be in you, John</hi> 14. 17. and ſaid, <hi>but the comforter which is the holy Spirit, whom the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will ſend in my name, he will teach you all things</hi> (mark what that is, that teacheth all things) and bringeth <hi>all things</hi> to your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance whatſoever I have ſaid (and ſo that is within which bringeth the words of ſpirit and life to remembrance) <hi>John</hi> 14. 25. 26. and having ſpoken of other things, he ſaith again, <hi>But when the comforter comes, even the Spirit of truth,</hi> John 15. 26. <hi>and if I go not away, the comforter will not come, but if I depart I will ſend him unto you,</hi> John 16. 7. <hi>and I have many things to ſay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, but you cannot bear them now,</hi> howbeit <hi>when he, the ſpirit of truth is come, he will guide you into all truth,</hi> John 16. 12, 13. here it may be ſeen that they who followed <hi>Chriſt without,</hi> and not received <hi>the ſpirit within,</hi> could not bear what he had to ſpeak unto them, and alſo, it may be ſeen that when the Spirit <hi>was come,</hi> it would be better with them.</p>
               <p>And much more might be mentioned, how Chriſt foretold, what was to come, and be received, and revealed in that day, <hi>John</hi> 16. 23. when the ſpirit ſhould be poured forth according to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets; <hi>all which plainly declareth, and moſt evidently ſets forth,</hi> how Chriſt in his Miniſtry, when he was upon earth, <hi>did moſt thief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly direct, unto the miniſtration of the ſpirit of Truth,</hi> which was then yet to come; and that they might not run to teach others (as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny do now) before they had received the ſpirit of truth <hi>in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,</hi> by, &amp; <hi>with that</hi> to be led into all truth, but might receive the power of truth <hi>in themſelves,</hi> from the life thereof, to convert others <hi>into the ſame,</hi> therefore ſaid he further, after he was riſen again, <hi>but tarry ye in the City of Jeruſalem until you be endued with power from on high, Mark</hi> 24. 4. ſo that, though they had ſeen his body before, &amp; had now ſeen him after his reſurrection, yet that, and all the reſt was not enough without the power, and the ſpirit, which was to come, which they were to wait for, and ſo now men ſhould tarry, wait, and ſtand ſtill, to ſee the ſalvation of God, and until they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the ſpirit, for it is the ſpirit (not the body) which ſearcheth all things, and ſheweth plainly of the Father.</p>
               <p>And by this before written in ſhort, I have a little endeavoured, to ſhew unto the meek and ſingle bearted, <hi>That</hi> Moſes <hi>when he was upon earth, directed unto Chriſt;</hi> As in theſe words,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Lord thy God will raiſe up unto thee a Prophet, from the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:51734:6"/> midſt of thee, of thy Brethren, like unto me, unto him ſhall ye hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken,</hi> Deut. 18. 15.</p>
               <p>And Chriſt when he was upon earth, directed unto the Spirit, which was to come, in the like words, ſaying,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theſe things have I ſpoken unto you, being yet preſent with you, but the Comforter which is the holy Spirit, whom the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will ſend in my name, he ſhall teach you all things,</hi> John 14. 25, 26.</p>
               <p>And then, what if I did write after the manner of men, and ſay, if <hi>Moſes</hi> were now upon the earth, and <hi>Chriſt</hi> in his own bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy upon the earth, and <hi>Moſes</hi> with all his Prieſts, Tyths and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, and Religion, which diſcovers ſin, but makes nothing per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, which <hi>Paul</hi> profited much in; if he I ſay, ſhould <hi>command and exhort all people under his Miniſtry, to go to Chriſt, and hear him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And if Chriſt were now upon earth, and notwithſtanding his outward Miracles, Circumciſion, Baptiſm, Supper, and Death, yet he ſhould <hi>command and exhort all,</hi> (that come through the Law or Miniſtration of <hi>Moſes</hi> unto him) <hi>to look, and tarry, and wait for another Comforter,</hi> That they might receive the Spirit in them, and ſay unto them, that <hi>that ſhould teach them all things, and lead them into all truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then whether or no, people were to continue following <hi>Moſes Prieſts,</hi> with their Tyths, and long prayers, and ſtill be ſeeking the Law at their mouth, <hi>or to come to Chriſt,</hi> to ſeek the Goſpel? for <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelf did not ſay, that they ſhould ſeek the Goſpel at the Prieſts mouth: And then, when did the Prieſts ever preach the Goſpel?</p>
               <p>And then, whether thoſe obey not <hi>Moſes,</hi> who leave the Prieſts and come to Chriſt, (the Light) and whether ſuch when they are come to Chriſt, ſhould alwayes be looking and following after his Body, Miracles, Baptiſm, or Supper, <hi>without them,</hi> or tarry and wait to receive the Spirit <hi>within them?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And then, which of theſe now, ſhould all people that profeſs Chriſt, be led by in theſe dayes, either <hi>Moſes, or the perſon of Chriſt, or the Spirit of Truth?</hi> And, whether ſuch as have received, and are truly indeed led by this Spirit of truth, and know that to be their Teacher, and follow it, and are ruled, governed, and guided by it, according to the command of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> do not hereby o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:51734:6"/> the command of <hi>Moſes</hi> and of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and fulfil their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine? And whether any other people or profeſſors whatſoever, do obey the command of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but only ſuch? And whether this be not a thing of great concernment to be known and learned, by all which profeſs Chriſtianity?</p>
               <p>But why then do people follow theſe Prieſts of <hi>England</hi> any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, which are contrary to <hi>Moſes,</hi> and alſo to <hi>Chriſt;</hi> who have no Store-houſes, but ſuffer the poor to want within and without, and the Widdow and Stranger ready to periſh, and moreover de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, and can never have enough of the ſpoil of others mens goods?</p>
               <p>And why do others diſpute about, and talk of the Body ſo much, which they never ſaw nor knew? And is it not better be ſilent, and know God, who dwels in his people, and the Spirit of Truth, which he requires in the inward parts, and to feel after God, even the life in themſelves, becauſe the Apoſtle ſaid, they were ſaved by his life, being before reconciled by his death, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 10. and until the life came, there were many things, which they were not ſaved from by his Body, for the Body was before the death, and the death which reconcileth, was paſſed through, before the life was received again to ſave and juſtifie.</p>
               <p>And why then, are people ſo much buſied about that which was before the reconciliation, (and ſo therein much ſhort of the life) and for outward <hi>Bread, Wine,</hi> and <hi>Water;</hi> Are not theſe, <hi>things</hi> which are ſeen? And are not the things that are ſeen temporal?</p>
               <p>But Chriſt the true Prophet being come, of whom <hi>Moſes</hi> did write, who is the end of the Law, and ſo the end of that Miniſtry, whereby that is done away for the weakneſs and unprofitableneſs thereof, and Chriſt coming after <hi>John,</hi> of whom <hi>John</hi> bare witneſs, that he was before, and greater, and came after him; and Chriſt alſo having <hi>finiſhed</hi> that which he himſelf came to do; and likewiſe ſo largely and often exhorted to wait for <hi>another Comforter, even the Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then what Miniſtration is it, that now ſtandeth and remaineth, which is according both to <hi>Moſes, Chriſt,</hi> and the holy <hi>Scriptures?</hi> and what Miniſtration is to be expected or waited for, but the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the Spirit? And whether all they be not compaſſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with a cloud of error, who are upholding that Miniſtry of the Law, (or a worſe) which Chriſt is the end of, and the Apoſtles ſaid was done away; and likewiſe ſuch as are upholding, and keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:51734:7"/> up that which Chriſt ſaid he had finiſhed? And, whether the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding of ſuch things now, be not quite oppoſite, both to <hi>Moſes Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Scriptures?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And being that <hi>Moſes,</hi> nor indeed his true Miniſters of the Law, <hi>are not upon earth,</hi> neither that Body of Chriſt, (which by the Profeſſors was murthered at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>) viſibly to be ſeen <hi>upon earth;</hi> then what was it that thoſe have to follow, who have not received the <hi>Spirit to be led by?</hi> and if they will ſay, they have <hi>the writings of</hi> Moſes <hi>and the word of Chriſt;</hi> I ſay if that be all, then they that forſook and denyed Chriſt, had more than them; for they had the words from his own mouth, which was <hi>Spirit and life,</hi> and yet they underſtood not; (and then what do thoſe underſtand who have not ſo much as they had?) therefore after he had ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and roſe again, he opened their underſtandings.</p>
               <p>And ſo, what is all their Religion worth, who are not come to the Spirit? And whether <hi>Moſes</hi> Miniſtration being ended by Chriſt, and Chriſt alſo having finiſhed his work, are not all people in the firſt place, now to wait for the Spirit, and to receive the Spirit by it, then to be led into all Truth; and ſo being firſt led into the Truth, then in the ſame Truth to worſhip God in the ſpirit, who is a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit? And whether there be now any true worſhip ſtanding, which God accepteth but only this? And whether this alone be not agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to <hi>Moſes, Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Scriptures?</hi> And then whether all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther worſhip now upheld, be not contrary to this true worſhip of God, and contrary to <hi>Moſes, Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Scriptures;</hi> and indeed chiefly oppoſite to the ſpirit of God, whereby he is grieved? And if ſo, whether all ſuch worſhip, way, practiſe, performances, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and Ordinances, (ſo called) be not better left undone than per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, until Gods Spirit be received to guid therein?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Concerning the Miniſtration of the Spirit, which abideth for ever.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MOſes</hi> and his Miniſtry were viſible, and Chriſt in the form of a ſervant (and ſo like unto <hi>Moſes</hi>) was viſible, and ſo was his miracles, and that which is viſible to the natural eye, the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal mind can come to profeſs, and contend about, but the bleſſed eye, which God openeth with the Light, cometh to ſee, the one
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:51734:7"/> done away, and the other finiſhed by Chriſt, the Light and Life.</p>
               <p>And the Spirit is that which firſt moved, and yet moveth, and moved unto, and led through the viſible Miniſtration; and this ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is inviſible, as it is written, <hi>the inviſible only wiſe God,</hi> whom no eye of fleſh hath ſeen, or can ſee. and this moving inviſible ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God which is without limit or end, is that which all people ſhould be led unto, by all its outward viſible appearances, miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and diſpenſations, and this ſpirit was that which gave forth and ordained the miniſtration of the law, which was glorious in its time, though to be done away: but how much more glorious is the miniſtration of that ſpirit of life it ſelf, from which the miniſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Law came, which ſpirit abideth for ever; And the Second <hi>Adam</hi> is made a quickning ſpirit, and the ſpirit which is the word was with God, and was God, before the body of fleſh was made, and that ſpirit abideth for ever, as is heard out of the Law, <hi>he ſhall abide for ever,</hi> and this is that which ever liveth to intercede.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And, this for ever bleſſed inviſibe ſpirit was before time, and is to be, when time ſhall be no more, and is without limit; an eternal lively ſubſtance, giving life from it ſelf, and ſecretly covering it ſelf from the carnal part of man, not ſeen nor underſtood, but by ſuch as by its ſecret motions comes to be led to ſee through that which ſhadows it forth, and by the Image, Forme, Shaddow, or Figure, to diſcern the ſubſtance, which is the life, where immortality dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth; for in the moſt innermoſt and ſecret of all, is the life of all, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing couered over with that in which it lies; through the which it breaking forth in any diſcovery of it ſelf, is that whereby the behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders might be drawn through the diſcovery to it ſelf, which in the diſcovery broke forth; for the diſcovery was ſtill too ſhort of that from whence it came, &amp; that which was diſcovered forth in any ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, Forme, or Image, was not to be Idolized, nor ſet up, for the every thing or ſubſtance of life, from whence it proceeded; and herein hath been much miſtake, by ſuch, who came not by that, which opened in the viſibles, to that from whence it came, in that, to have their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings opened, and thereby to be made ſenſible of that which is eternal, by it to be brought in, where its indwellings abideth fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, whoſe breakings forth in the viſible (which was to draw to that inviſible) refreſhed the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ul inviſibly, in an unexpected manner, and time; but being</hi> (after) <hi>ſought for in the viſibles
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:51734:8"/> (and not in the eternal) Withdraws it ſelf out of the viſibles, and out of the ſight and reach of that which ſeeks it there, that thereby, that which is to live for ever with it, may come through all that which it appeared in, unto the very thing, and inviſible ſubſtance it ſelf which is the life of all, and the true center of the living mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which moveth of it ſelf, and gave forth all things good, as they proceeded from it, by vertue of its gradual, and various motions; and this being come, openeth it ſelf in them that find it, and live therein, and this maketh Darkneſs Light before the people whoſe dwelling is with God; and the crooked comes to be made ſtaight by the thing it ſelf, and dark ſayings of old comes to be opened, and ſecret things revealed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to write more plain for the ſake of the weak, of this glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous indwelling ſpirit, which in the fulneſs of time cometh forth in fleſh laying hold of the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> the moſt glorious appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that ever was, being thus appeared was the expreſs image of God, who dwelleth in his people, whoſe bodies are fleſh and earthly tabernacles; but by the operation of the ſanctifying clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſpirit, which the Father ſendeth, are made fit habitations of God, and ſo co-heirs with Chriſt, and members of his body, fleſh, and bones; which Spirit quickneth to God, and being thus recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and obeyed, is felt to live for ever, though the ſhadowings forth of it be done away, and this is eternal and never endeth, but abideth with ſuch for ever; and the miniſtration of it, is life it ſelf to the ſoul, and more to be valued, and deſired, than all that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was ſeen before it.</p>
               <p>And as the Lord took of that ſpirit which was upon <hi>Moſes,</hi> and put it upon his brethren, the Elders of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> whereby they might Rule, and judge with him; ſo ſaith Chriſt, the Father ſhall take of mine, &amp; give unto you, even of that ſpirit of Love, Life, Power, Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, and Vertue, which was upon and in him (that was like unto <hi>Moſes</hi>) is miniſtred into, &amp; put upon ſuch as are truly his brethren, &amp; friends, whereby with him they (thus gifted, ſanctified, and quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied) judgeth the world, for all judgment is committed to the Son, and of that which the Son hath (and is committed to him) doth the Father give unto his members, and ſo from Chriſt the head, they come to receive power over the World, and its Way, Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and Faſhions, and over unclean ſpirits. And that is an unclean
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:51734:8"/> ſpirit which will lead into any ſin, and it is an unclean ſpirit in which ſin ſtandeth, and which pleadeth for the continuance, and uphol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of that which is unclean, and that is of the World, which the Saints judgeth.</p>
               <p>And as thoſe Elders of <hi>Iſrael</hi> (who were of the Church in the Wilderneſs) were not made fit <hi>to Judge, nor Rule in outward mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> by all the writings and words of the law (though received by diſpoſition of Angels) until the Lord himſelf took of that Spirit which was upon <hi>Moſes</hi> and put upon them.</p>
               <p>So thoſe that profeſs to be Elders in the Church now, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perſon whatſoever, are much leſs made fit to <hi>Rule, or Judge in ſpiritual matters,</hi> by all the reading and profeſſing <hi>Moſes</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, and Chriſts words, and the reſt of the holy Scriptures (though they were given by the inſpiration of God) until the Lord take of that ſpirit, which was upon, and in Chriſt (who is like unto <hi>Moſes</hi>) and give unto, and pour it upon, and miniſter it in unto them. And this is done in Gods way (which is ſecret) and time (which is in his own hand) to thoſe whom he accounteth worthy thus to honour, and who truly waiteth for it, as a wayfering man for a reſting place, and as a Captive for deliverance.</p>
               <p>And though Chriſt (after his reſurrection) ſaid, All power in Heaven and in Earth is given unto me, <hi>Go ye therefore and teach,</hi> yet they were to tarry until they had the power in themſelves, and when that was come, which they were to tarry, and wait for, then with that they went and ſo taught the Nations, from the ſenſible feeling of that which taught them how to teach, and all thing elſe, when the ſame Spirit and power was upon them, which was before committed unto him; and ſo the coming forth of it from him into them, and filling them therewith, was to them in that work of the Miniſtry moſt effectual, like as the vertue going forth of Chriſt healed the woman; ſo the power and vertue of the holy ſpirit, coming forth from Chriſt, being ſent of the Father, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by the Diſciples (who with much deſire waited for that<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>) impowered them to do that which before they were commanded to do, after they were endued with power (or had the power in them) and ſo what they were commanded to do, they were to wait to receive power in themſelves, from God to performe; and Chriſt did intend to give them power to do that which he commanded: and as he commanded them to go and teach, he alſo required them
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:51734:9"/> to tarry (<hi>and ſo not to go</hi>) until they had received power ſo to do, and ſo it was the power of the Holy Ghoſt in them, which made them Miniſters<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and theſe were, and ſuch are, truly Ordained Miniſters: And after they had received power from on high, even the ſpirit (or life) of truth, and were filled therewith, and ſo had it in them, then they went to do that which was commanded them, then they went to teach the Nations, and converted thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, and turned ſinners, and brought ſoules to God, and then they were called Chriſtians, and then were people brought to be of the true Church which Chriſt buildeth, upon that which fleſh and blood revealeth not.</p>
               <p>And this is the entrance into the Church of God, 2 <hi>Theſ. 1. 1. the receiving of the ſpirit,</hi> and in this God is worſhipped, &amp; not elſe for this hath excluded all, other worſhip, and thoſe only are the true worſhippers, who comes in thus by the door, which is Chriſt, the light and ſpirit of truth, ſent into the heart from God.</p>
               <p>And if all the prudent learned Divines (ſo called) in <hi>Europe,</hi> or all, or any of the wiſeſt Orthodox men (ſo call'd) in any other quarter of the whole World, can prove (by the Scriptures of the Old and New Teſtament) any other true worſhip of God (who is a Spirit) now extant among men, and to be performed (eſpecially among them called Chriſtians) with acceptance to God, <hi>but only that, which the ſpirit of truth leadeth ſuch unto, as receive it;</hi> then let them bring it forth that we may ſee it, and prove it by plain undeniable truth of Scripture; or otherwiſe I ſhall look upon their proofs, words, wayes, actions, practiſes, performances, duties, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral worſhips as things of no value.</p>
               <p>Or if there be any other entrance into the true worſhip of God than this Spirit that God ſendeth (or the Light which leadeth to it) or if there be, any other worſhip which God doth, or will accept to be after this, ſpoken or propheſied of in the Scriptures of truth; whereby this ſhall ever be done away, or ended from being the true, only, and alone worſhip of God, whil'ſt men have a being up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth; then let the wiſeſt of the Sons of men bring it forth, and produce there ſtrong reaſons therein, that we may plead together, and that the entrance into, and the true worſhip it ſelf of the only true inviſible God, may be declared over all the World, for the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of every tender heart concerning this.</p>
               <p>For this I am ſatisfied in, that Chriſt Jeſus (who is the end of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:51734:9"/> the Law, and who finiſhed his work, when he was upon earth) is made a quickning Spirit, and is the way and truth of life, which bringeth into the worſhip of God, and he is the beginning and the end, and he leadeth to the beginning of Gods Worſhip, and he is the end, and the Reſt of all the faithful, in whom all the promiſes are yea and Amen; and without him all is as nothing, and all that come before him are thieves, and robbers, and he it is that abideth a Prieſt for ever, and his ſpirit of truth is it which all people, and profeſſors whatſoever, ſhould firſt wait to receive, thereby to be led into that true ſpiritual worſhip, which alone God accepteth; leſt they, and their worſhip, and building fall together, in a day when there is none to deliver.</p>
               <p>And then thus I will Query. If Chriſts own dear Diſciples who had forſook all and followed him, <hi>(not Prieſts or Baptiſts)</hi> did not come to receive this ſpirit, by hearing all the words which he ſpoke unto them, but by waiting after the words were ended; then, whether thoſe that have not forſaken all (nor ſo much as the worlds faſhions) do now come to receive the Spirit by Reading, Hearing, or Profeſſing the ſame words of Chriſt, now written, or any other part of Scriptures?</p>
               <p>Or whether a proud man hath received this Spirit, or a lyar, or a prophane perſon, or any wiſe, or prudent man whatſoever, by any means or way of his? and whether any ſuch ever did, have, can, or may by any induſtry, or other way, or means, attain to this ſpirit which leadeth in the true Worſhip of God, but as it is freely given forth from God? and then, whether all people are not to be led by that ſpirit (which God freely giveth) into the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God; becauſe Chriſt ſaid, <hi>the ſpirit ſhould lead,</hi> which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed doth lead into all truth and nothing elſe doth ſo? And they that hath not received this from God to lead them, are not yet come to be led by that which the Sons, and Children of God were, and are, led by.</p>
               <p>And the Miniſtration of the Spirit, which all are now to be taught by, is inwardly to be known, in the neareſt, ſecret inviſible manner, and is more out of the ſight, comprehenſion, and reach of mans wiſdome, than any other Miniſtration; and it is given forth from the clear fountain it ſelf, unto the ſouls ſatisfaction of man, when he is come to the end of words; or having heard much, or all the words that can be ſpoken of it, remaineth unſatisfied, in a
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:51734:10"/> reſtleſs longing deſire to find, receive, feel, and enjoy the thing it ſelf, which the words declared of; and that which ſatisfieth the true thirſting ſoul, comes clearly from God to the refreſhing of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward parrs of man, and filling of the empty, barren, hungry ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which cannot be ſatisfied without Gods in-dwellings; and thus the diſciples were led along, and at laſt, in a fooliſh way to the great Profeſſors they waited among them in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and the Lord had regard unto them, and ſent his own Spirit unto them, and then they were filled with the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>And the ſecret inviſible hand of God, whoſe power was &amp; is felt in my heart, having out of the ſight of fleſh and blood, in the hidden counſel of his ſecret will, led me by the vertue of the opperation &amp; drawings thereof, through thoſe things, which thereby I come to leave behind, and to receive and feel that which now goeth before, and is my leader, in whoſe Covenant of life eternal, my ſoul is now ſatisfied; and ſo by good experience of the Lords leadings, and from an experimental knowledge, and ſenſible feeling, and preſent enjoyment of the incomes of the Spirit of Truth and Life, which fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the inward parts with the holineſs of it ſelf, and giveth power to do the things required before of God, even from the right and good underſtanding thereof, is this written; That where it meets with the like condition in a weary Traveller, it may anſwer its own, and be helpful to the weak and feeble, that ſuch may not give over preſſing forwards, nor faint in their long travail, though many Mountains on which they did nouriſh themſelves for a time, will not yield them Bread now; yet that they may with me, and the reſt of the followers and friends of Chriſt, (paſt and preſent) alwayes continue following the Spirit as it leads, until the inward man be filled therewith; and ſo power and ſtrength from God come to be known, and received in every particular.</p>
               <p>For thus it is with Chriſts followers now, they are not ſatisfied until they are filled with that which they heard of, and their ſouls thirſted after, and ſo it was with them then, &amp; they were filled with what they wanted before; and then, from that which they were fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with, they ſpoke forth; and ſo they did teach the Nations, and brought people under the power of God, and Baptiſed them into that, and dipt them into the Name of the Father, and brought them under that which ſaveth from ſin, and plunged them into the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit; and as they Teacht they did this, Baptiſing as they did
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:51734:10"/> Teach, and plunging them (as their doctrine went forth) into that which waſheth and purifieth the Conſcience from the filth and guilt of ſin, of which the outward Baptiſm was a Figure of this which ſaveth; and ſo their Doctrine was from an inward life, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from that which was inviſible; and ſo reached to that which wanted life in the Hearers, and ſo brought up the power of God over them, and them under it, and into it; for the word is <hi>Into;</hi> and they were to bring People <hi>into</hi> the Name, (not water) and they were to bring or Baptiſe them <hi>into</hi> the Name, <hi>as</hi> they did Teach, Go ye and Teach, <hi>Baptiſing into;</hi> Baptiſing is in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Tenſe, when they did Teach; and ſo here the ſpiritual and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Baptiſm goes along with the preaching of the Word of life, which is inward, and brings man to an inward injoyment of God, being Baptiſed <hi>into</hi> his Name, which is a ſtrong Tower, which preſerveth from the power of the Devil; and we all who are brought into this, and are come in here, are all by one ſpirit Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed into one Body, and ſo worſhip God in the ſpirit, having the heart ſprinkled from an evil Conſcience, by the waſhig of Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in the Miniſtration of the Goſpel of peace, whereby there is a drawing nigh to God, (being brought into his Name) and a free acceſs to the Throne of that Grace, which ſaveth from, and out of all filthineſs of fleſh and ſpirit.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
